I do a test when I come in like in a
company and ask them okay what are you
doing about your gen if they're all
telling me about model training I know
this going to be hard
s you're listening to the AI native Dev
brought to you by Tesla
[Music]
hello everyone Thanks for tuning back in
to the AI native Dev today I am excited
to dig into the analogy of AI native
development and how does it compare to
devops to Cloud native development and
to really offer a a bright perspective
about that we have Patrick deis who has
done many many things across his career
on it here we'll just emphasize that
he's one of the core drivers and leaders
in forming the devops movement created
devops days and has has really shaped a
lot of what we think of as modern devops
today and the practices and has spent
the last year or two immersing into gen
and how that really impacts software
development and such so Patrick thanks
for coming on to the show yes and and
it's exciting right so these new
technologies and some people might not
expect this from me saying okay it's
sculture first there's two things
obviously there's tools and there's
culture in this case but yes I'm excited
inde I fully agree I think the analogy
is quite strong so I guess maybe we
start indeed with that question is do
you think the analogy between AI native
development and and Cloud native or
devops is that an apt analogy when you
think about the the magnitude of change
here you think about what we need to
consider in it does it feel like a
usefulness an apt lens yeah I think over
my career there's been these kind of
like instrumental technology moments
right and then it's always something new
and whether that was the mobile or all
of a sudden was serverless or clout
native and KU this there's always this
emerging kind of feeling that you're at
and those kind of new technologies we
often in the beginning don't know
exactly where it leads to we we're
trying and playing with this but
ultimately they have an influence on the
way we work I would say that the Gen if
I look back the speed of impact that is
drastically different right right all of
a sudden you can share something
tomorrow somebody can use it it goes
into production so that speed is
definitely different than when the early
Cloud native days were emerging people
were trying to figure this out it's much
easier to interweave it into the
activities than it was before I guess
maybe aspects of cloud were a bit
earlier right like S3 for instance I
think pretty quick adoption is it about
the ease of adopting into into your
workflows or is it just about the sort
of the sex appeal hype travels
definitely faster but looking beyond the
hype I think the almost like the tools
like using an llm have being so
democratized like you didn't in the
early days of cloud first you had to
spend some inform infrastructure and so
on but now if I'm a lawyer I can use
chat GPT I can use open Ai and it's
there that kind of gets it much faster
in usage and also has everybody much
faster on the train because they see the
possibilities how this doing and that's
different but I think that is due to the
salification of things that is so
commoditized and so easy to get that
yeah that's really interesting so it's
easier to provide a solution that is Gen
I powered and as a result of that there
are just many more yeah although I
wouldn't want to be in open AI shoes
serving the world so that part is not
different like from a scale perspective
and you have to support everything so
that's definitely the speed the impact
the compan is playing into the hype the
new technology the startups the funding
that's there right that kind of like
rocket ship doing this and that's been
instrumental in pushing this forward
similari again nobody in the beginning
of cloud native knew exactly how we've
seen many iterations before we got to
more standardized thing like a kuber
Naes everybody settled on but before
there there was like numerous iterations
and this is where I feel we're at we're
like in the fast iteration phas today
this company's hot tomorrow there's
going to be another we're just churning
through until we settle on a base that
kind of not saying the winter takes it
all but it could be in very different
forms every time there's been a new
release there's also the problem of this
being like a thin veneer layer on top of
an llm that people are and it I'm not
saying it's useful yeah but everybody
can start building this as such and so
that's that fast building is really
different uh than in the past if you're
looking for more similarities maybe on
the cultural side in the group I
experienced early bringing AI into a
company in the product that the teams
that were doing thei or kind of the the
Engineers there they were not used to
production there were somewhere and I
always joke there're somewhere in there
assuming in their data Lake nobody knew
building reports and all of a sudden
they became star of the show right so
that that kind of friction I've seen
firsthand of one group not working
together with another group and
obviously was the same with Devon Ops
and bringing them closer together
because we need to get into production
there is value there and we need to
bring that to the End customer and
that's definitely a friction point I
think it was called in this time not
shift left guy but it was shift right
getting them closer to production and
that's definitely also a cultural change
in kind of a an organization I love that
point around breaking the silos just
like we did between Dev and Ops or you
know was a key a key driver there but
also with the data I remember a
conversation with one of the lead
security people in in one of the big
Banks who was talking about how he's
been spending years cultivating his
relationship with the development team
and working on it you can debate if he
is or isn't happy about it but it's deep
he knows who to talk to they've had a
longtime conversation and suddenly
there's this whole horde of new people
that he needs to talk to that he hasn't
he doesn't even know who he's supposed
to talk to and they don't don't know who
he is and what concerns and he had
security concerns like where is this
data even coming from and do you know
you can trust it etc etc but it's also
true for operations it's Al true for
anything production so that's a really
good point and I guess have you seen
organizations take it on in that type of
Outlook right thinking about hey what
have we done around Dev and Ops most of
the initial projects are often done with
the data science folks or something
because they're closest to the kind of
the data they can achieve the
functionality right a lot of what I hear
from companies is this is where the
incubation happens in the company they
understand the lingo a little bit but
then they often lack like we mentioned
like going to production and kind of
bringing that in is where you bring in
the engineering a lot of people in the
data science think hey I have a Jupiter
notebook and I'm I'm good right we can't
run this on production and and I
definitely seen companies deliberately
putting infusing either the data science
team with more engineering or
traditional engineering folks to deliver
the proof of concept and not just to
stay in the kind of Eternal mode I do a
test when I come in like in a company
and I ask them okay what are you doing
about your gen if they're all telling me
about model training I know it's going
to be hard sell because the company is
overrun by the data science folks and
they will tell you like the data needs
to be perfect
and we to get everything I believe the
new game is about integration much like
devops was about integration of the Two
Worlds I do not need to know have a deep
understanding of all the algorithms but
I can definitely put it to use and
that's why I'm also so attracted to this
field because I always had an eye on the
data science folks but the math went
behind my brain yeah but this game I've
been doing for a long time and there's a
lot of similarities on how do that
integration and bring that to production
yeah I think I really like this analogy
and I guess if we think about devops you
had some companies that they called it
they created these devops teams which is
ironic but we have these it's fine that
they're called devops teams but often
times these devops teams were actually
not trying to break silos what they were
doing is this is the team that uses
infrastructure code they're the puppet
and Chef users on it and therefore
unlike their predecessors in Ops they
are coders a little bit they know how to
build things maybe they're at some point
even using terraform but they weren't
tackling the culture shift so it feels
maybe it's a little bit like that right
you have your AI Engineers today are
being formed they might know how to
build applications out of these llms or
like Wrangle llms to do something
effective and they might Traverse
further back into the actual data
scientist but there might still be a gap
to the production side of it indeed yeah
yeah and who would you say needs to fill
that Gap if you were to optimally set up
an organization how do you imagine it
would be set up in terms of
responsibilities when there's a new
technology and again you can have the
mobile team being a new one it doesn't
matter right so they're the incubators
and then you have to make a choice in a
way that are they just going to be the
team that always takes care of this and
in some companies that makes sense oh
it's the chat team the chatbot team and
right it's the only thing they do but if
you're set out to for example say all my
Engineers when they're building I want
them to be able to use these new AI
Technologies to do certain things faster
to to get better results then I would
have to scale up my traditional
Engineers with some training right so I
would use that AI data science team and
say you're now the mentors of what goes
on in the other teams it could be the
same as the developer experience team
it's an enablement team that goes across
your organization right who goes into
each of the teams and helps them get
bootstrapped it's the point is not about
making them all the experts because they
will stay the experts much like the
devops folks were not supposed to get
everybody to do all the devop stuff
right but just enough that they know
when to ask and things they can do
themselves so that's scaling out the
knowledge as a pattern in the different
organizations there is then if you
continue that Journey there is also a
part where there's shared infrastructure
I do not want all the teams to run their
llms in a different way I I do not want
to have guard rails in every different
flavor so you see more of a
standardization happening and that's
similar like when you have a few teams
and you can build like guilds around it
exchange it but then the infrastructure
in my belief is very similar to your
Cloud infrastructure but it's just thei
infrastructure that could be a proxy
that filters things that's how you
monitor things that's a centralized way
of getting feedback so you see those are
similar to a cloud catalog of services
we're going to provide all the teams
with an AI Services catalog and say if
you need this and then we are working
the same way as this is the paved Road
right this is the standard sound sounds
like familiar terms now yeah yes and
then if you want to deviate it that's
fine but your cost so in that way I I
see the scale out and these this is what
I see companies like Cisco or adobe
they're taking the same pattern of one
team enabling the other team scaling
this out and then absorbing the central
pieces into your platform and it's not
just about the infrastructure it is the
enablement on the infrastructure and
then it the governance that you put on
that centralized pie because that's
another problem that you all have to
take care of in each of the teams if
you're using this I don't want you to
use these kind of models yeah how do I
not force but at least make sure that
you know about this and and put that in
in guidelines yeah makes perfect sense
to me so if I go back a little bit here
you start with the digital
transformation team monitor whatever
some specific group that is specifically
enabling something that now has heavy
use of llm right maybe it didn't even
exist before right now you have it the
rest of the company continues to operate
as they had before or maybe they have
some interaction with this group but
generally it's an addition it's a
specific product and so you don't need
shareed infrastructure because it's just
this group when a second a third group
forms and things like that now you start
needing okay I've got some shared
infrastructure and so that might require
that sort of platform team starting to
have you know governance uh capabilities
starting to have some uniformity as you
expand into some future I guess that was
true for cloud and it's debat for AI or
llms do we get ourselves to a place in
which everything is llm powered you can
make that case or not I think in Cloud
it felt obvious at some point which is
everybody needs a server to run on and
so you know you will run on the cloud
and and run that fashion with theyi may
be a bit more debatable but the more you
expand it the more you need to have
enablement have those and I guess you
get into shared responsibility mode as
well now it's okay someone else is
running these llms maybe even
constraining you with that paved Road or
really making your life quite difficult
to deviate from it so maybe I chose a
specific partner Enterprises do this
today right I've chosen one of the
specific Foundation models to partner
with and So you you're constrainted you
have to use that but then within that
sendbox or within those boundaries the
application teams are the ones that and
it's not just about running your own
llms like even if they're all a SAU
version of the llm yeah you still have
to say we're going to put the right like
check marks for the policies in place
we're going to make sure that we have
volume discounts much like we CDN costs
dealing with so those are all things and
and again one of the important Services
people keep forgetting is when you put
these things out yes governance guard
rails but Gathering feedback from the
end users to make it better that's also
a component you do not want each of the
teams to do and tracing observability
all those kind of things fit in that
group again it's not about having your
own infrastructure but it's like
managing that kind of Suite of services
and offering them as a kind of a
standard package so maybe let's talk a
little bit about within the organization
the culture or different aptitudes that
you need amongst those people that that
work because in devops that was
significant right part of it was
technical enablement or maybe the skills
of knowing how to work with a cloud or
knowing how to work but then there were
all these other things for instance
probably most well known is the pace of
delivery right the sort of the
continuous deployment and the notion of
much more Dynamic software development
process which require different people
in in devops indeed there were people
that needed to become coders or be a
little bit more comfortable with code
from being sis admins I guess when you
think about AI you think about those
teams maybe put aside the actual
concrete data scientists think about the
software Engineers that are working with
these systems do you see a similar
culture shift required what are the
different skills or aptitudes needed I
think I've hit most of the times the
discussion around these llms are
non-deterministic so therefore we cannot
trust them therefore we cannot use them
but mostly it is about people not
understanding how you test this more
reliably again I'm not saying it's
perfect and but it's dealing with
uncertainty that's a shift that people
have to go through and once you explain
them that there are certain ways to do
this that limit this then you got them
over and become more engineering
practices again otherwise it's more yeah
it looks good to me but hey I I don't
know how I should do this the second
thing that usually I see companies do is
while getting their engineering teams
excited on AI and the new technology
they also get them excited about the new
set of tools that help them in the new
job because that kind of if they see the
power in their day-to-day job yeah
they're also likely to get more excited
on using this because they they want to
understand how this works and go from
there if they're excited by co-pilot and
whatever seeing how that makes them more
productive they're more excited about
adding a co-pilot like capability into
prodct yeah yeah yeah but they don't see
the value there they're going to be
quite negative on using the tooli and
bring it into their kind of product as
well so I found I I very much relate and
experience the joy if I was to air quote
it of the lack of predictability of of
the LMS and not knowing it's very hard
to evaluate them maybe we'll dig into
that a bit more Dez trainer founder of
intercom who an early episode here on
the podcast said that you basically need
to make peace with the fact that you
don't know if your product works and one
of the thoughts that I had was it's
actually quite analogous to
it's another step change in the same
direction that we had when we Shi
software more continuously right when
you went from these recorded releases
that were thoroughly tested or annual
releases that were thoroughly tested
that you felt like your confidence level
around what we said we are doing is
actually what we were doing was very
very high to a plac that really
celebrates many releases in a given day
and observability in knowing whether
your product works or not by observing
it in production yes you add test you
don't just blindly ship the software but
embracing this not that the tests May
Fail or rather that the test may pass
and that the product May Fail in
production and be very well instrumented
to identify that happened to roll back
and to learn from it or to gradually and
it feels a little bit like maybe llms
take it to another level like I really
have no idea but all these concepts of
these Canary releases gradual roll outs
observability the ability to roll back
and all those are kind of the same tools
right is it is it fair to think of it as
is another order of magnitude or another
step in the same direction in terms of
what should your Ops and software
delivery practices be I think in Ops
we've always dealt with chaos because we
all understand that in theory everything
should be great for the customer but in
reality we look at our log files and
it's not right so in that way yes the
observability is one step in the right
direction to know you know when you're
dealing like first there's monitoring
and then there's observability it did
what in production let me check that for
you so that's where you see a lot of
people put that in production to see
what the customers are experiences then
I guess we learned that in the cloud
architectures we were no more
architecting for that one machine that
could not fail we architected an assumed
failure right right and I'm seeing this
kind of is happening also here if the
llm might not give the right answer what
are we doing to control this we're not
going to put this in to decide whether
you get a or not you could it's probably
not the best use no but understanding
what use cases is the failure yes or no
we had one interesting example is that
we used actually the ux to our advantage
so llms can generate the text and let's
say a year ago they were not always that
fast right so we use that to our
advantage that the customers and the
users knew it was being generated by AI
so they had to bring more attention to
verifying this we had icons
with a sparkle on there that meant its
AI so again this is not technical but
these are cues of like warning also
people saying this is not perfect it
doesn't mean it's not helpful and they
can just reload and retry and regenerate
and that's fine but sometimes you see
it's not always that technical that
needs to be perfect it's your architect
around this and kind of deal with the
imperfection yeah there yeah that's a
good point and it's actually maybe an
advantage that AI gives us that we
didn't have in the cloud because in the
cloud the customers generally didn't
know and didn't care if you're hosted on
the CL or in your own data center their
expectation of uptime or of performance
all those are the same whether you're
hosted on the cloud or you're a Data
Center and with AI there's in certain
use cases a certain level of Tolerance
maybe that we're getting because users
are also willing to adapt their ways
which is a card or an opportunity that
is a helper for those building the LM
based product within this world though
it's convenient and there's a lot to
learn from indeed this path of saying
okay you have to really be good at this
and this analogy keeps coming up I had a
conversation with Armon from from Hashi
Corp on a recent episode and we were
talking about how if you want to do
selfhealing and all sorts of you know
crazy things in your Ops stack then
actually the the way to be best equipped
to do that is to already be very good at
uh operations and be accumulating if you
already accumulated an instrumented all
your system you Comm to this data
observability data iteration data all of
that about your system you can proba
inform the the llm based tool or LM
powerered tool that is trying to do
self-healing better and therefore you
can do self-healing better so there's
like a compounding effect basically the
teams the halves and the Have Nots are
growing further apart in in that
operations and I guess here it's another
it's another muscle in the same vein
because because you get better but I do
think some aspects of it like the
evaluation they get extreme right when
you ship a new product for instance even
when you're very obsy very Dynamic for
iteration for improvements you can work
in this type of incremental roll it out
do it in small bits involve it when you
ship a new capability you you need to
have a certain level of confidence that
it is above a bar to be able to ship it
and and I guess that's proven very hard
on some capabilities in the LM world
what is the view that you formed around
evaluation around this quality and and
the ability to assess it in the world of
Elms we made some great strides there
the evaluations in the beginning were
more if when you were building your own
llms and that was built for that and
obviously they have a lot of money and
they can spend a lot of time building
the perfect data set but for your use
case because that's usually what it
boils down to like I build something for
my use case and it's not like a standard
available test set that I have so yes
you have a domain expert creating
questions but now we actually have llms
assisting us to write better questions
and to ease the generation of those
evaluations better so that's one way
that's the synthetic way of creating
those evaluations together with the
domain experts and then the third source
is actually when it went wrong from
production is feed those examples back
into your test evaluation set so that
kind of improves it but that's why that
return aspect is so important that you
notice the differences is it perfect by
no means but it is changing one comma in
a prompt will have different results so
that's why we've learned that we need to
have that test set it doesn't need to be
a million things you test but at least
the most common cases that gives you
that impact feel if you change a model
likely your tests are going to be
different and then you need to tune your
prompt a little bit there is on the
other hand also a new not a new but
something that's going to help us is
tools like dpy that actually rewrite or
refactor prompts based on what the model
is we're using so they're getting more
clever on yeah much like we do
refactoring of code but refactoring the
prom because they know this is the model
you probably want to phrases like this
so we get a little bit help almost like
a transpiler of prompts in there again
not perfect but we've come a long way
from doing the manual thing to having it
more assisted and then you get into the
feedback loop very similar to your code
where you say okay this evaluation no
this is not good okay I prompt with a
better one so that's the test battery
that you're doing I think what we
learned was very important is that often
testing is seen as something the
developer does but we learned that to
actually write those tests and the
questions of the domain is something
that needs to be moved to the product
owner and they don't do this in code
they don't do this in prompt but they
need a system that actually allows them
to do this quite easily and see the
impacts of the changes and do the
validation so there's a little bit of a
shift from testing is for the engineers
although we already had that problem
with business Tes and so on but this
moved up to actually the product owners
again and to an extent that's a shift
further left element because you're
going further Upstream to the
requirements but it's interesting it
sounds like you're describing on one
hand very much engineering action of
basically better instrumentation of your
testing process we need to learn from
failures I think in the past the tests
were binary if they passed great if they
didn't pass you only used the failures
momentarily to get them to pass but we
didn't actually try to store that data
or do anything interative and now it
feels like maybe we should think about
testing processes and workflows somewhat
in in a similar way to what we think
about operations and and systems we need
to capture and learn from the failures
as well so we can optimize and tune our
systems and that's very like a technical
piece so that piece maybe moves from Ops
to Dev hey Dev you need to learn a
little bit from your Ops counterparts to
do those and then further left in the
product side is you have to Define what
good looks like what it means that the
product works and what it doesn't what
versus not because that's going to have
to be codified but much like we reuse
the testing from the bdd to test actual
the monitoring production yeah this is
the same thing here right you write your
evals but then you have a specific set
of evals you're basically you're running
all the time as a health check because
maybe the model change something right
on aite or something you don't know but
you will notice the difference and
that's like you don't run your full test
Suite but at least the more
strategically test
but I agree but I think in in general
the key takeaway here is the notion of
evaluation the notion of knowing what is
correct and incorrect in your product
has really jumped up in importance
because you have to assess these
unpredictable systems and see what they
are what they're doing an interesting
and slightly unpleasant thoughts to
think about whether laggers might
actually have a little bit of an
advantage but I think putting on my
history that again every time there's a
new technology in the beginning people I
think that's only valued because first
part of the problem is making work and
then you progress into more maturity
okay we need to repeated and then have
to prepare for failure so on so I think
that's only normal that I as that
question as Meetup you've been live now
for five months and how do you test and
then you you hear like crickets right
because they're still doing oh let's get
to me yeah and if you can do it and to
us definitely not something you can do
at scale and debate TD or not it's very
much still yeah yeah that's a good thing
and I guess what we said before how
users give you some slack that's
probably temporary as eventually users
are if you want me to use this tool it
should work it's your problem it's
unpredictable just make it work it all
looks very easy in the beginning but
getting it
robust it is something that you have to
work with and you have to really change
your strategy is really feels like a
craft in the making feels like a new
it's not entirely unique because we had
these typ of un untrusted or unreliable
pieces of our software development and
so it's hard to find your soft
methodology around so if I look of how
devops as a profession has matured first
20% was infrastructure as could
eventually we rearchitecturing
engineering because then failure you
already touch back yeah we were assuming
these Sy will break and we're not sure
why that is the dreams is all the agents
take care R our jobs but the reality is
they're not going to be perfect that's
inherent in the technology it's not
perfect so you can actually replay the
AG to a point and then you can go from
there sometimes it generates multiple
options so you get to choose people are
starting to figure out not just the
initial kind ofal so maybe sometimes
it's hard even the term like AI engineer
are you're referring to software
developer with are referring to someone
who building like applications
about an agent AI agent that is writing
code for
youu but as you point out things are
moving so quickly that it's not
something that's inherent in this domain
the terms will solidifi as Dev say never
like fully settled and I guess what we
need to do and we're doing it right here
is sharing the learning sharing the
perspective you know maybe at the moment
on many different stages but at least
many people are hearing it I think as
long as we continue doing that we'll try
to consolidate where is relevant just
keep the sharing going thanks Patrick
for sharing all these great views I
think those learnings and I recommend to
everyone to follow Patrick LinkedIn all
the social networks he has all these
super
experiments doing it because we've been
doing all sorts of interesting kind of
Hands-On work of what does it actually
feel like to voice a cursor and so we
don't have time to cover all of those
unfortunately over here but recommend
you try that out so thanks again Patrick
for coming on and thanks uh for everyone
for tuning
[Music]
[Applause]
in thanks for tuning in join us next
time on the AI native Dev brought to you
by Tesla
[Music]